<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation against transportation of leather.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 506.h.10[86]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892793</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">187182</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 187182)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C7:1[86])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation against transportation of leather.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1603-1625 : James I)</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most Excellent Maiestie.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Westminster the one and thirtieth day of March, in the sixt yeere of our reigne ...</note>
                  <note>Revoking any patents for export of neat's leather or hides. Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Arms 10; Steele notation: louing curious 2) Leather seruice.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hides and skins --  Law and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:187182:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of England's coat of arms in 1608</figDesc>
               </figure> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> By the King. ¶ A Proclamation againſt Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Leather.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas we vnderſtand, that diuers of our louing</hi> Subiects haue made complaint, that the price of Neates-Leather is lately raiſed to ſuch a height, as it prooueth very grieuous to the poorer ſort, who haue dayly vſe thereof: Such is and ſhall be euer our care and reſolution to preuent, or reforme all things that may be burthenſome to any of our people ouer whom Almighty God hath committed to Vs the vniuerſall care, as we haue bene no leſſe curious to finde and ſearch out the true cauſe, then to prouide for the remedie of the inconuenience, And therein particularly to be ſure to take away all meanes or colour for any ſuch grieuance, that may (either in trueth or apprehenſion) ariſe from any action of our owne. For which purpoſe, although We doe dayly ſee by common experience, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue prices grow vpon our Subiects by the practiſe and greedineſſe of priuate perſons, who either by Foreſtalling and Ingroſſing of Commodities, or by combyning to keepe them at high prices, or by conueying them out of our Realme by ſtealth, doe increaſe the rates aſwell of forraine, as home bred commodities, without any Acte of ours: Neuertheleſſe, becauſe We haue obſerued that ſome euil affected people, in this, as in diuers other things, are more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to impute the cauſe of grieuance to ſome thing done by vs, then to reſort to the maine and originall grounds of the ſame; Wee haue for more ſurety, cauſed our Councell to take Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what Licences We haue giuen, (which haply may haue bene ſome pretext for abuſe in that kinde) and thereby finding that ſome ſmall quantitie of that commoditie hath bene Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by vertue of a Licenſe granted at our firſt comming, at the Suite of ſome forraine Princes our Allies, whom Wee could hardly then refuſe, although it be knowen to the world, that We did not giue Licence for any Leather by name, but generally for the Tranſporting of forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Commodities, and that onely to the ſumme of ſixe Thouſand pounds in value, which could
<pb facs="tcp:187182:2"/>be no occaſion of ſuch ſcarcitie: Yet becauſe it is not vnlikely but that ſome Neates-Leather might be hereafter iſſued by vertue of that Licence (as ſome hath bene already) contrary to our meaning, Wee did not onely (ſo ſoone as this came to our eares) giue preſent order to our Treaſourer of England to reſtraine all vſe of Licences (if any there were or be) concerning the Tranſportation of ſuch Leather, whereof there is no ſuch plentie within our kingdome, but that whatſoeuer is caried away, may bee ſoone felt in the ſcarcitie and deareneſſe thereof at home, But for the more ſure preuention of this grieuance, and that all our louing Subiects may be witneſſes of our care in this behalfe, We doe now by theſe preſents reuoke and diſanull all Licences and Tolerations concerning Tranſportation of Neates-Leather, (if any there be) And do further expreſly prohibite and forbid all maner perſons whatſoeuer, That they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt not from hencefoorth to cary or conuey away, or cauſe or conſent to be caried or conueyed away out of this our Realme, any Neates-Leather, or Neates-Hides raw before they bee perfect Leather.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe We doe by theſe preſents ſtraightly charge and Command all our Cuſtomers, Comptrollers, Searchers, Surueyors, and other our Officers of our Ports, That they doe not onely informe our ſaid Treaſourer, what Neates-Leather, or Neates-Hides raw they haue knowen to be Tranſported at any time ſince the beginning of our Raigne, at what Ports, and by whom; But alſo that they be from henceforth watchful that none paſſe by any practiſe, pretence, or colour Whatſoeuer, as they, and euery of them will anſwere the contrary at their vttermoſt perils. Knowing that from hencefoorth they ſhall haue no excuſe by pretence of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences or other Tolerations, inaſmuch as we haue reuoked and diſauowed them (if any ſuch there be) by theſe preſents. Willing yet further all our Subiects that can learne or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any abuſe in this behalfe, That they alſo reſort to our ſaid Treaſourer and informe him thereof, whereby he may detect the fraud, corruption, and confederacie of our ſaid Officers, if they ſhall conceale the ſame. And ſuch diſcouerers ſhall receiue ſuch reward as their ſeruice ſhall deſerue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Giuen at our Palace of Weſtminſter <date>the one and thirtieth day of March, in the ſixt yeere of our Reigne of great Britaine, France and Ireland.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie. Anno Dom. 1608.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
